So I made this image gosh, I don't even know the specific year,
you probably have a better sense of the actual year that I made it.
But I'm guessing it was 2016, 2017.
And it was for the mini app MPD,
150, which is I understood it was group trying to, you know, bring some consciousness
and intentionality around the specific date of the 150 year anniversary of the Minneapolis Police Department.
I just really knew that this was the kind of image I wanted to make because I had these photos already.
My brother is a really great photographer and he was in college in DC at the time and I was living in DC.
And so I he had taken these pictures of an action that was happening related to the Notico to Access Pipeline in 2016,
in which they, you know, occupied the the National Mall with these TPs.
And I just knew this was the image I wanted to make because Minneapolis has a really significant role in the history of
indigenous activism in particular.
It's where a lot of the American Indian movement founders and organizers, a lot of them hailed from that area.
It's also just had such a long history and history of colonialism of the United States.
And learning, you know, that the Minneapolis Police Department was 150 years old, you know,
even without doing a research, I was like, okay, so very clearly and very, very early on.
The police department was like most assuredly involved in policing indigenous people in that area because Minneapolis still remains one of the highest, you know,
urban centers for Native people right there, kind of at the crossroads of
initiative and Dakota, Dakota peoples.
And I think what I was hoping to get out with it was just shaking up people's imagination a little bit more around,
around police it, right?
Like this view, like 150 years sounds like a long time to an individual, but, you know, in my tribe, we talk about,
we've been here around, we've been around for 6,000 years along this river that I'm literally right next to right now.
So 150 years is nothing, right?
It's just a tiny portion of even a thousand years and just trying to open up some space for people to imagine that if,
if they didn't always exist, if the police in this formation didn't always exist, then surely they don't have to always exist.
So the way I actually created the image was basically taking the image itself, reducing the number of colors in it.
And then just going in and kind of replacing, like selecting all of the colors on it and replacing it with different colors.
And so then it was just a process of trial and error, figuring out what the palette is that I wanted.
I'm a huge fan of high contrast neon, asked neon to pastel kind of color palettes.
And then the text, I must have heard it somewhere, like at standing rock or in some abolition learning spaces and Washington DC.
And that was something that I just found so evocative about the actual action action and DC was, you know, here it is in this place that was dedicated to, in many ways, making indigenous people people passed.
And using these structures that are at least in media coded as being historical, primitive structures and it being used in a very contemporaneous way.
And yeah, I think that, because my background is actually in performance, not in visual design.
And so I'm often more inspired by like the drama, turgy of different activism and how, how activists are able to.
Bring into contrast these different ideas and so yeah, I'm whether you mentioned that because I was definitely an inspiration from the action itself.
There is a performance specifically it's called it's called the indigenous for a discovery, which I did in.
For the first time in 2016, leading up to the presidential election, where I did what I call unsettling tours of the Smithsonian's presidential portrait gallery, just trying to bring some critical consciousness, because I just remember going to that museum and seeing like.
The only mission that made it people in relation to the president's was like they said like, and Jackson's complicated relationship with tribes.
And I was just like, OK, so people don't know nothing about the relationship between tribes and presidents, you know, and of course, president just being the stand in for federal government for settler colonialism.
And so that I definitely associated with that that's how I like kind of had this context around Minneapolis settler colonialism like 150 years that timing just seems so.
You know, specific.
Yeah, and I've done that performance a few more times at other museums and also back at the Smithsonian a few times as well.
Awesome. Thank you for sharing.
Yeah, I will say just as a thing about the image, I do have.
With one area of attention around the image, which is me as as someone from a tribe who doesn't have this tradition around TVs.
Making use of that image.
And I don't have a good answer for it.
I've asked people from those communities what they thought and everyone's been like positive around it. Some push back on the message itself.
But in terms of the depiction, most people haven't said anything negative to me, but I'm still like kind of.
I would have I would have feelings about someone using a very Kataba thing in a different situation, but yeah.